<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ashwin's Blog</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/</link><description>Recent content on Ashwin's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Building an App with ChatGPT</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2023-05-11-building_an_app_with_chatgpt/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2023-05-11-building_an_app_with_chatgpt/</guid><description>Last month, I started to build a personal finance app using OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s ChatGPT. Over the course of 30 hours, I saw my app idea come to life, all thanks to the power of AI. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience and the lessons I learned while working with ChatGPT.
The code can be found here: https://github.com/ashwin67/finhandle
ChatGPT as a personal assistant The process was incredibly smooth - I&amp;rsquo;d provide ChatGPT with a requirement, and it would generate Python, JavaScript, or HTML code snippets based on my request.</description></item><item><title>Managing Time</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2023-02-25-managing-time/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2023-02-25-managing-time/</guid><description>Just one year back, I was struggling to find enough time in a day. I wanted to run more, read more books, work on a hobby project etc but always felt that there wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough time in a day. Then, I read the book Atomic habits about which I blogged last year. The book by James Clear set me on a journey. Whether I should commend the book or myself, I do not know.</description></item><item><title>ChatGPT</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-12-04-chatgpt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-12-04-chatgpt/</guid><description>Can you believe that none of the following including the image was written by me! All I did was to ask chatGPT to write a conversation between a software engineer and a photographer about AI technologies and conclude about the future. I provided a similar prompt to Dall-e
Software engineer: Hey photographer, have you heard about the new AI technologies that are coming out?
Photographer: Yeah, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a bit about them.</description></item><item><title>A 6 DOF Robot</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-07-23-a-6-dof-robot/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-07-23-a-6-dof-robot/</guid><description>Ok, so here is the final robot being operated using Rviz and Moveit packages of ROS. The nice software from ongdexter made it easy to get the AR3 working.
But before I got here, there were several challenges. I wrote about some of those in an earlier post: A 3D printed Robot. For example, sourcing the components from all over the world, struggles with the 3D print settings, fixing bearings, set screw troubles etc.</description></item><item><title>Software Languages</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-07-11-software-languages/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-07-11-software-languages/</guid><description>Most software engineers I know can program in multiple languages. Based on the domain in which they work, it can be anywhere between 2 and 10. On a regular basis, I use Matlab, Python and C++. Infrequently, I use many others like Java, Rust, C, batch etc. The interesting thing is that switching between languages is not a big deal these days. Why is that?
When I started programming in C two decades ago, I installed turbo C, followed Kernighan &amp;amp; Ritchie&amp;rsquo;s C Programming Language book and made programs to test my knowledge.</description></item><item><title>Some DIY jobs</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-07-03-some-diy-jobs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-07-03-some-diy-jobs/</guid><description>My robot had become a bit too heavy to carry around. Also, it would trip over if I made quick movements in certain directions. So, I gave it wheels, a support for the arm when at rest and some adjustable legs.
A €10 transport roller, some adjustable cabinet legs, a few screws, a plank and a few hours with the tools got me what I wanted. A job done plus great satisfaction on a Sunday morning.</description></item><item><title>Github copilot</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-26-github-copilot/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-26-github-copilot/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you do not know how to program in Rust but you do know programming itself. You will need to install rust, create a project etc. After that, you can just start programming in Rust.
While I am writing some things, most of the code is actually written by Github copilot. I just need to tell github copilot what to do and it just does the job for me. This makes it really easy to learn a new language.</description></item><item><title>A 3D printed 6 DOF robot</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-19-a-3d-printed-robot/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-19-a-3d-printed-robot/</guid><description>I decided to build a 6 DOF robot in January. Since mechanical engineering is not my cup of tea, I decided to use an open source project. After some research, I found Chris Annin&amp;rsquo;s AR3 robot. You get all the 3D files, the component list of things to buy and also some basic software to run the robot. I had built robots at work but there was a whole team to do those.</description></item><item><title>An atomic habit</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-11-an-atomic-habit/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-11-an-atomic-habit/</guid><description>A couple of months back, an office colleague suggested a book called atomic habits by James Clear. It talks about a framework that can help you improve yourself every day. Suppose you want to improve your fitness, you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t simply get a gym subscription because you would just quit that in a few days. Instead, you could start with 10 pushups every morning immediately after brushing your teeth. Now that takes just 1 minute and is easy to cultivate that as a habit.</description></item><item><title>Robot projects</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-05-robot-projects/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-06-05-robot-projects/</guid><description>It was 2010 when I got a job at Bosch to work on a &amp;ldquo;cutting edge&amp;rdquo; lawnmower, now called the Bosch Indego. At that point, there was only one famous robotic lawnmower, the Husqvarna. They had very smartly patented a critical piece of technology, the perimeter wire which would be laid at the borders of a lawn which would sense and thereby help a lawnmower stay inside the lawn. Without this, it was quite hard to safely prevent a lawnmower from trying to mow the street or the neighbor&amp;rsquo;s garden.</description></item><item><title>3D Printing</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-01-23-3d-printing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-01-23-3d-printing/</guid><description>Adhesive tape used to be my son&amp;rsquo;s favorite tool when he was younger. If he broke a toy, he could fix it with some tape. Torn paper, no problem, we have tape. I used to tell him that a tape can&amp;rsquo;t fix everything. But one day, we were watching the Hungarian Grand Prix when Max Verstappen slid in the rain and then eventually finished 2nd with a damaged car that was fixed with speed tape!</description></item><item><title>Hobby projects</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-01-18-hobby-projects/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2022-01-18-hobby-projects/</guid><description>When I was 18, my dad bought me a computer. It was a pentium P4 with 128MB RAM and 40GB RAM and cost about 35000 Rupees. A personal computer was still a luxury for any lower middle income family like us. If I am not wrong, it was probably two months of my dad&amp;rsquo;s salary (or maybe more). He never asked me if I made the best use of it. But I always wanted to make something using the computer.</description></item><item><title>Electric car charging</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2021-07-17-car_charging/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2021-07-17-car_charging/</guid><description>Electric cars are great. Except for the upfront cost of buying the car, every other aspect is great. One of the most important considerations is about the charging infrastructure. We bought the car more than 3 months back and learnt several new things.
Range anxiety is a non issue! Every day, we drive the car for 150kms. Typically, there is still 250kms of range left in the evening. Just like we charge our phone, we charge the car in the evening for 2 hours and it is full again.</description></item><item><title>Social media and the erosion of truth</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2020-08-26-social_media_and_the_erosion_of_truth/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2020-08-26-social_media_and_the_erosion_of_truth/</guid><description>Of all the changes in last decade, probably the biggest of consequence is the erosion of truth. Twenty years back, if a person told you that he believes the sky is just a curtain above us hiding aliens from us, he would have been laughed at. Today though, he could easily create a community of like-minded believers and feed on each other&amp;rsquo;s madness. Am I exaggerating? Just check the number of believers in a flat earth or the number of Qanon supporters.</description></item><item><title>The covid situation</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2020-06-03-the-covid-situation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2020-06-03-the-covid-situation/</guid><description>Until 2019, things looked bright everywhere. Millions of people coming out of poverty everywhere. GDP numbers of almost every country increasing year after year. Billionaires were increasing. The world seemed to be really marching at full speed. There were geopolitical issues and wars in some parts of the world threatening to slow this forward march. But who would have thought of a complete brake on the the world&amp;rsquo;s capitalistic machinery!</description></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2012-09-03-artificial-intelligence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/post/2012-09-03-artificial-intelligence/</guid><description>Let us say, we are looking out of a beach under clear blue skies towards a few ships sailing away. How did we know that we were looking at the sea, above was the blue sky and those were ships.
Isn&amp;rsquo;t it quite amusing that we have a name for everything that we want to name? And that we have learnt how to differentiate between those names? Would a 3 month old child know how to differentiate between the sky and the sea, considering that both are blue?</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashwinupadhyaya.com/about/</guid><description>I am a software engineer who can&amp;rsquo;t sit still. I am always looking for new things to learn and new things to build. I am either working on some DIY project or learning a new programming language or framework. Sometimes, I am running a half marathon or traveling to a new place. Time is the most precious resource and I try to make the most of it.</description></item></channel></rss>